welcome to meditating with John Breaux
Vicki I am a cognitive psychologist and
cognitive scientist at the University of
Toronto I scientifically study
mindfulness and related phenomena like
Insight flow mystical experience wisdom
I I have been practicing the past
meditation meta contemplation and Tai
Chi for 29 years and I've been teaching
it professionally for almost 20 years
for those of you is joining for the
first time this is a progressive course
there's teaching classes on Monday and
Thursday and then there's sitting just
sitting on Tuesday and Wednesday Friday
and Saturday there are no classes on
Sunday you're welcome to stay with us
but I recommend what you do because this
will be recorded as you back and look at
day one and find the lesson there with
your way through to the other lesson
days and catch up on what you've missed
and then you can join us tomorrow if you
wish so today I want to talk to you
about the the third thing you're going
to find for your core for my manures is
designing a challenge to me so I'm going
to be leaning up against the wall just
to give myself a little bit of extra
stability so what we're doing today is
like I said we're going to learn how to
find your flow now this has to do with
something that people at least associate
with meditation and it's a correct
Association but typically how they frame
it might be wrong this is your ability
to get very sort of absorbed in your
meditation really really get deeply
engaged and involved in it and people
think this is sort of a matter of will
sort of got a will myself in and we'll
talk more about this on Thursday with
getting the right kind of concentration
but it's not really a matter of will its
instead it's a matter of engaging what's
called flow as I mentioned I study folk
scientifically and I published on it in
the Oxford Handbook of spontaneous
thought with Leah frog an area in Para
Bennett and the basic idea wife Lois was
there was study first
sort of explicitly a developed by chicks
that Mahina book called flow this like
it's for some of you are interested I
believe it's the second video came from
the meeting crisis series when I talk at
length about flow and what's going on
there for our purpose is flow is that
state you know when you're we are
engaged in the task and it's so
involving that you're sort of a looser
sense of the normal passage of time
everything seemed sort of super salient
right but not airing sort of egocentric
mainly in your mind how am i doing what
are people thinking falls away because
you're so absorbed in the task you know
that you're exerting a lot of effort but
it seems effortless people get it under
dancing its sparring playing jazz rock
climbing so what we're trying to do is
engage the flow state because the flow
state we're going to get learn how to
get really more involved and really
almost welling within our meditative
focus that's a skill you have to
practice and you also have to set the
conditions up correctly notice what I
mentioned about the flow state what
people are in the flow state that report
that all that chatter in their head goes
way because of the intensity of their
involvement so instead of thinking of
this as willpower to give it more as
increasing involvement so what are the
conditions that get us into the flow
state but what we have to do is you have
to put it you have to put a challenge on
yourself so that the demands that you're
putting on yourself jobs throughout the
edge of your skills you have to really
engage all of your skills in order to
meet the demands and that there's a
constant sort of shifting on the demands
you have two key sort of ratcheting up
the challenge you need very clear
feedback and your actions and the
response from the environment has to be
tightly coupled well how do we bring
that into our meditation and then how do
we also integrate that with what we're
trying to cultivate and mindfulness was
it which is an increasing sense of being
present and coupled to an environment so
following I'm gonna teach you how do you
expand and enrich and enhance your
awareness with your attention so
normally when people are following their
breath or following their breath so I'm
just gonna talk right now don't start
doing this I will talk you through the
exercise when we're in the set okay so
when people are following their breath
they've got this little little sort of
spot here perhaps where they're actually
fueling dispensations so after we've
taken time they'll be silenced and
you'll Center and you're rude all three
lines will bring their attention to
where we're going to follow the breath
and then I'll ask you to expand your
awareness so expand it over your abdomen
remember we talked about increasing your
interoception and integrating it with
your introspection so we're going to
expand it over your abdomen and into
your abdomen like if somebody was asking
you how's your stomach feeling inside
like when you have a doctor okay so
you're gonna expand right I'm gonna ask
you to enrich your awareness what do I
mean by that is try to pay attention to
many different kinds of sensations their
sensations of movement temperature
texture tightness and also different
patterns of sensations will
automatically constantly for you so what
you're doing is you're simultaneously
distinguishing different kinds of
sensations right and you're also
expanding your awareness and letting
patterns form so you sort of zooming
your awareness out and yet you're
actually a good at that I'm gonna hold
this up and I want here to quickly read
it okay so the cat now notice how you
read this as an H and this is an a even
though they're the same because what
you're doing right what you're doing is
part of your attention is going up to
the whole word in order to disambiguate
the letters but part of your attention
is also going down to the individual
letter so you can actually read the word
and you're doing that simultaneously in
a highly dynamic and flowing manner and
that's what you had to do to develop the
skill of read it so what you're doing
right here's an object this is my frog I
carry a frog but not this one I carry a
frog around in my pocket as well frogs
are a symbol from the Oh plate
and for self-transcendence because they
start in one world and they transform so
that they can live in another world so
like in each spot where it's called the
optimal grip if too close to the details
I lose the whole if I'm too far back on
the whole I lose some of the details and
what I'm constantly doing depending on
the task is I'm prep on there just
moving around the world with your
attention you're integrating the
features and the whole together in a
constantly flowing that flowing manner
so you get sort of a optimal grip now
what you're gonna do is do exactly that
you're going to be expanding your
awareness and also trying to notice the
different kinds of sensations and then
the patterns of spontaneously form and
that's going to be challenging it's
going to be quite challenging and that's
the point if you were trying to get you
into the flow state while also improving
your optimal grip on your intro
exceptive awareness
so we'll do flow here all right and then
I'll ask you to wash your attention here
and you'll pick up the breathing in your
chest you'll use that to anchor your
attention and then you'll expand your
attention over your chest and then into
your chest and then you'll orig orig
notice the different kinds of sensations
right all the details you're getting
that very fast move you know dynamic
between the whole and the parts and
really challenging yourself to get into
the flow state and we'll repeat it with
the shoulders and then your spine in
your back and then you'll have your
whole of your torso and then what you're
going to do is you're going to try and
follow the whole of your breath with the
fall of your torso so I know right I
feel all of my torsos moving with my
breath now the way to think about that
is when you come to meditate see how
about your frog is focal you have a
focal awareness but you still have a
surrounding peripheral awareness of
everything around your frog you'll have
a focal awareness of you have you done
to get where you follow your breath but
you'll maintain your peripheral
awareness throughout the whole of your
torso of the flowing of your breath
now it's really really important in this
exercise and in the practice of flow to
things that you're centrally rooted
right and that you do not hyperventilate
it's really important you don't
hyperventilate people try to start to
hyperventilate because they're trying to
force their breathing into a longer
period issah t so that they have more
time do this as best you can with your
natural breath they would hyperventilate
okay all right so we're going to set the
timer in a minute we'll begin when I say
begin so remember there's gonna be
silence for a while you're gonna take
time because you're gonna find your
Center for example for me I find it just
away from the wall and then I'm going to
lean back to stabilize myself because my
metier is something you need to do that
because of your back pain or other
issues you might have then you're going
to do
finding your route all three lines front
back Center and then I'll speak into
speak and what I'll do is I'll talk you
through the finding your flow and
remember when I say go into meditation
your focal awareness is here but you
maintain a peripheral awareness
throughout the whole of your body this
really anchors you in your body really
enhances your interoception an
intersection that they parts of the
brain that you use for interoception are
the same parts of the brain that you use
to pick up on other people's mental
states there's a deep connection between
finding your flow and your ability to
become aware of other people's mental
states which is very central to
compassion and to meta okay alright
let's get ready make sure you're
comfortable okay let's begin
bring your attention to your don t on
don't hyperventilate span your awareness
across your abdomen in the end to your
abdomen
I'm trying to pick up on different kinds
of sensation temperature movement
tension you need spontaneous powder this
is challenging expanding your awareness
and also enriching your West
so we wash your attention wearing this
up to your heart area feel the movements
in your chest being generated by your
breath use that to anchor your attention
and begin to expand your awareness
across your chest
and into your chest deep inside
now begin to enrich your awareness try
to pick up on different kinds of
sensation different know sensations a
temperature attention tightness movement
location may be spontaneous patterns
that they form
don't hyperventilate
now integrate the flow at your chest
with the flow in your abdomen one flow
try to leave that running naturally in
place and your attention to your
shoulders there gently rocking with your
breath use that motion to anchor your
attention and begin to expand your
awareness throughout the surface of your
shoulders and then deep into your
shoulder muscles
sensations
different patterns that spontaneously
arise and pass away
we have to create the flow at your
shoulders with flow in your chest we
activate that flow in your chest
let me reintegrate the flow in your
chest and shoulders with the flow in
your abdomen reactivate the phone your
abdomen
one whole field of sensations flowing
together
I'll gently bring your attention to your
back your spine especially there's a
standing wave that moves up and down
your spine with your breath don't
hyperventilate use that standing wave
moving up and down your spine to become
aware of motion in your back with your
breath use that to anchor your attention
have you expand your awareness across
all your back top middle and bottom and
then sink into your back muscles
now enrich your awareness pick up on all
different kinds of sensations and
patterns of sensations
with the flow in your back merge with
the flow in your abdomen flow in your
chest flow in your shoulders don't
hyperventilate make sure that you feel
centered and rooted bring your yourse
focal attention to your Dante and keep
your peripheral attention throughout the
whole of that field the sensation so
you're following the whole of your since
your breath with the whole of your torso
your focal awareness is on your Dante in
your path is most pronounced but you're
picking up the rippling effects
throughout the whole of your torso now
begin to meditate
you
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you cultivated in your
practice if your everyday consciousness
and cognition try to carry that state of
mind and that state of body do you open
your eyes and look around your room
zwei obviously that you're not going to
get their way it's gonna take years but
this is how you get their practice
integrating state of consciousness and
cognition there you had in your practice
with your everyday consciousness and
cognition okay so we're gonna take some
questions this is from the Kennedy High
neck makes a former student of mine I
initially taken but passed the course
that instructed counting to ten while
sitting should I label that habit as
counting to what seems to be the expense
of a better quality sit if you're if the
practice is working for you then use it
I'm going to show you a practice on
Thursday that's very similar for finding
appropriate concentration there so you
might be as want to do the counting
rather than following your breath and
you debate everything else that works
too
I find following the breath without the
counting is better long term because
then you can sort of do it without any
sort inner words happening but that will
take time and so if you're finding that
the practice works for you you should be
able to integrate it with what I'm
teaching you the next is from Nick
Nicholas I don't have time for a full
meditation session but still want to do
the routing process can I only do the
center route it seems to be the
strongest have the strongest impact if
you genuinely don't have time yes
find your Center find your route maybe
follow your breath for four breaths just
do that basic then just do that basic
thing continuity of practice is way more
important than quantity of practice this
is from Steven what to do about internal
resistance if the time comes and I
strongly don't want to meditate
one day should I listen to my intuition
or should I force myself to keep up with
the practice so on when we get from
teaching lesson six I'll tell you how to
deal with that resistance what I suggest
is if you're getting a strong inner
resistance and there isn't a genuine
therapeutic or traumatic issue involved
you should just practice Center and Rudy
just factor senator Rudy maybe finding
your flow what I'll show you later to do
is once you that's a little bit more
stabilized when you get those strong
feelings of resistance they can actually
become your meditative focus so you
could what you can do is you could
meditate on the resistance and then
you're already meditating you're already
meditating even though you're
experiencing the resistance so try right
for now just finding your Center in your
root and and your flow and just try to
keep up the continuity and then a little
bit later we'll go over what I just
mentioned to you and that will help you
to deal with strong resistance one more
time though I don't know you do but if
there is some psychotherapeutic
or trauma issues that need to be there
are unresolved I'm not saying you have
that I'm saying if they're like if you
are considering treatment or you're in
treatment you need to talk to your
therapist about it that's a different
that's a different thing
from Lars what exactly you do mean by
patterns so what might happen is you'll
get sort of a bunch of tingling
sensations and they and they all feel
like they're they're sort of like
forming a weird shape it may not happen
for you don't worry if it doesn't if you
can just pick up on different kinds of
sensations but for many people what
happens is it's almost like it becomes
like music for them they can sort of
whether it's a sort of rhythm of these
sensations and the foreground of these
ones at the background that's what I'm
talking about don't you don't have to
force it if you can just do it I said if
you can expand and enrich your awareness
and so you're getting that sense of
being really deeply involved in your
introspective flow that's not that's
more than sufficient hi Lynn Lynn is
also a former student and colleague of
mine it's good to see you Lynn when I am
not feeling well in my body sensing all
of my chest seems to increase my
tenseness and worry should I return to
focusing on the avanti end if you're
what you're getting here is a lot of
intense tension yeah then just maybe
shift back to the rooting exercise and
root and release and let that go and
return to your dong kyun and then just
try and pick up on the flow in your
dog's head and then keep trying it maybe
every few days and then it gets tense
and tight and it's starting to cut off
your breath root and relax and fall back
into your daunting it and then keep
doing that until you can gradually erode
your way into being able to flow into
your chest that's a fairly common
pattern that live observed so that's a
useful thing to do when that happens
Hara Mina if we sense a pattern should
we label it is it paint if you said it's
a pattern you can label it if you want
try not to get too attached to it you
want to be basically flowing you want
your attention to be against zooming out
and zooming in zooming out and zooming
it you know I get locked in any one
place so let the patterns arise
I let them fall away if you if it's
helpful to you to label it that's good
to do another one from Nicholas how long
should the routing process take I barely
finished their front route by the time
you start with the new instruction yeah
I apologize for that but it's hard to
engage different people do that a
difference these I can't give you a
number for some people you know you
might be picking up half of your set
right now to Center it that's fine
that is fine it will eventually speed up
you'll be able to Center and route very
very quickly but there's no rush either
so you need to take that much time take
that much time and I'm Macready I seem
to have trouble sensing my Denton and
route when when routing compared to my
head and chest does this improve over
time very much that's an excellent
question
think about all day we're really hyper
focused up here we're like inverted
triangles that's where we're so easily
upset and you're trying to invert it so
that your attention is more distributed
this way and that will take time I
recommend if you can because this really
helps all of this and your question is
particular taking up a moving
mindfulness practice like Tai Chi Chuan
or yoga because they really help you
route and help you sort of gradually
erode where your breathing is until it
drops more deeply into baby breathing
okay so thank you everyone for joining I
want to as always thank you
- amar and Jason for all of their help
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next video you'll also
find helpful videos in general on my
channel about the cultivation of wisdom
dealing with our current crisis
situation as I mentioned there's video
on there explaining flow in depth
experience there is a talk I recently
gave on their link eating flow and
insight a missle experience all kinds of
things so there's you can get you can
set this into a broader context if you
check out some of those videos we're
doing this every morning at 9:30 except
Sundays
a reminder Monday and Thursdays our
Dharma days Dharma means it's like logos
it means teaching and structure and
realization so Monday and Thursday our
Dharma days Tuesday Wednesday Friday and
Saturday sit days there oh there's
always QA at the end of the sit so thank
you very much
keep up your practice remember if
quantity quantity of practice is way
more important the quality of practice
or continuity of practice is way more
important than quantity of practice
because what you're really working on is
a quality of awareness and attention and
also please remember to per find
yourself take a carry one thank you for
your time and attention